<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[0xa1ed]]></title>
  <link href="http://0xa1ed.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://0xa1ed.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-17T19:18:08+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://0xa1ed.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[0xa1ed]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Case For FreeBSD]]></title>
    <link href="http://0xa1ed.github.io/blog/2015/03/17/the-case-for-bsd/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-17T15:55:37+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://0xa1ed.github.io/blog/2015/03/17/the-case-for-bsd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>NOTE: This is a work in progress. Any suggestions for inclusion, or any errata you&rsquo;d like to point out can be sent to <a href="&#109;&#97;&#x69;&#x6c;&#116;&#111;&#x3a;&#48;&#120;&#97;&#x31;&#x65;&#100;&#x40;&#114;&#x69;&#115;&#101;&#x75;&#112;&#x2e;&#110;&#x65;&#116;">&#48;&#x78;&#x61;&#49;&#x65;&#x64;&#x40;&#x72;&#x69;&#115;&#x65;&#x75;&#112;&#46;&#x6e;&#x65;&#116;</a>.</p>

<h3>Intro</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve always had a great degree of interest in Unix-like operating systems, and I&rsquo;ve used and become at least intermediately experienced with most,
if not all, of the available flavours of Unix-like systems. For a number of years, I ran Mac OS X and Linux alongside one another, though I mostly
favoured using OS X over Linux, for the simple reason that I never encountered a distribution of Linux that didn&rsquo;t feel like it was cobbled
together somewhat randomly. That&rsquo;s a personal thing, I&rsquo;m not here to badmouth Linux on a technical level - I&rsquo;m almost definitely not qualified to do so,
even if I did have the inclination.</p>

<p>Towards the end of last year, reading up on OS X&rsquo;s history had me itching to try a BSD - a flavour of Unix long said to be in the domain of wizardly
neckbeards. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s unusable,&rdquo; they told me. &ldquo;Its community is full of hardasses!&rdquo; they screamed. Everyone I asked had some objection to BSD, largely
for no reason. Nobody I&rsquo;ve ever conversed with on my university degree or on the Internet has ever actually given me a <em>reasonable</em> explanation as to
why they&rsquo;re BSD-allergic. I suspect, on reflection, that most either haven&rsquo;t actually tried using it, or they&rsquo;ve never given it a real chance. In any
case, I&rsquo;ve always enjoyed a challenge, so I decided to do some research. After dabbling with a few different BSDs (FreeBSD, OpenBSD and NetBSD, namely),
I eventually decided to jump directly into the deep end with FreeBSD. Personally, I felt FreeBSD to be easier to use and understand than either of the
other two I tried out. If you want to know more about BSD in general, check out the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berkeley_Software_Distribution">BSD Wikipedia Page</a>.</p>

<p>FreeBSD is the unknown giant of operating systems. It has global influence, though many people (including, I suspect, some of its own contributors) don&rsquo;t
realise it. Most regular users of the Internet have never even heard of it. It is, however, part of the critical infrastructure of some of the busiest
networks in the world. As a server, it&rsquo;s famed for its stability and its uptime. <a href="http://www.scei.co.jp/ps4-license/" title="PS4 Open Source Components">Its kernel powers the PlayStation 4</a>.
WhatsApp use it for their servers, and <a href="http://www.theinquirer.net/inquirer/news/2382297/whatsapp-founder-showers-freebsd-with-usd1m-after-facebook-windfall">they recently donated one million dollars</a> to the project.
And as a final example, Apple&rsquo;s Darwin project, which eventually evolved into OS X, has its own roots in both 4.4BSD-Lite2 and FreeBSD, and if you dig deep
enough into OS X&rsquo;s innards, you can see it there.</p>

<p>Anyway, I downloaded a copy of FreeBSD 10.1-RC2, a kind of beta version of the upcoming 10.1 release of the OS (it has since become a full release, which
you can get <a href="https://www.freebsd.org/where.html">here</a>). I googled for resources to turn to for assistance, just in case something went horrible wrong while
installing it, and I landed on both FreeBSD&rsquo;s official handbook (available <a href="https://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/">here</a>) and an excellent beginners guide to setting up your own
FreeBSD desktop by Nicole Reid, which you can find <a href="https://cooltrainer.org/a-freebsd-desktop-howto/" title="Cooltrainer">here</a>. I mostly followed the latter resource on my first install, and I recommend
that you do too, if you decide to try out FreeBSD, because it&rsquo;s thorough and entirely easy to understand. I&rsquo;ve since installed 10.1-RELEASE on other devices
and used only the handbook for guidance, but Nicole Reid&rsquo;s guide is absolutely perfect by itself.</p>

<p>So, without further babbling, why should you use FreeBSD?</p>

<h3>Installation and Configuration</h3>

<p>Installation is ridiculously easy. I had a working system in well under an hour, and if you follow the guide I linked above, or indeed use the handbook, you&rsquo;ll
be absolutely fine too. I guess a lot of people find the idea of using a text-based installer intimidating, I don&rsquo;t know, but one of the most common insults
hurled at BSD by my peers is that installation is a nightmare. Again, I don&rsquo;t think any of these people have actually tried installing it.</p>

<p>Post-install configuration is easy. Almost everything is contained in text files, activated or deactivated using simple variables. Loading kernel modules is
easy too, even on the fly; type &lsquo;kldload aio&rsquo; as a privileged user and you&rsquo;re away with asynchronous input/output. If you want that to be permanent, just
insert a line that says &lsquo;aio_load=&ldquo;YES&rdquo;&rsquo; into /boot/loader.conf, and it&rsquo;ll load the module every time you boot. It&rsquo;s easy to do, and it&rsquo;s about as UNIX as it
gets.</p>

<h3>Additional Software</h3>

<p>You can use pkg to install binary blobs from FreeBSD repositories. Pretty much any software you could ask for is in there. GUIs, including GNOME3, MATE,
Enlightenment, Window Maker, Fluxbox, etc, etc, etc. Browsers. Mail clients. Instant Messengers. Intrusion Detection Systems. Compilers. IDEs. Media Players.
You can get all of these things and more using pkg. I sincerely think it&rsquo;s as good as any Linux alternative, and that includes Debian/Ubuntu with their vast
apt-get repositories. You can also get all these things through FreeBSD&rsquo;s ports tree, if you like to build things from source. That way certainly gives you
more control over the customization of your applications. It&rsquo;s advised that you don&rsquo;t mix ports and binary packages, though, so if you can avoid it, do.</p>

<p>For any software that runs on Linux, requires Linux-specific libraries, and doesn&rsquo;t work seamlessly with BSD, there&rsquo;s a Linux compatability layer you can
install.</p>

<p>I should mention, that there are notable cases of programs that don&rsquo;t behave well, or simply don&rsquo;t work at all, on FreeBSD. A major one of these is Skype.
It works with the <em>old</em> Linux compatability layer, but not the current one. I personally don&rsquo;t think that&rsquo;s a massive loss, because I prefer not to have
software on my FreeBSD machine that is riddled with NSA backdoors. I don&rsquo;t really have that choice with some other OSes I use regularly, but as long as I
have a FreeBSD machine, I&rsquo;d like to keep it relatively spook-free.</p>

<h3>Error Reporting, and the Community</h3>

<p>I feel like I had to tie these two issues together because, naturally, the FreeBSD community is one of the first places people turn when they run in to trouble,
which is fine, because they&rsquo;re great. Contrary to the claims I alluded to earlier, the FreeBSD community is not the unnecessarily harsh environment people like to make it out
to be. I honestly have no idea where that stereotype originated.</p>

<p>That being said, if you find some kind of software that doesn&rsquo;t work, or is out of date or something, there are a few things you can do (this goes for errata/bugs/etc in the base system too):</p>

<ul>
<li>Google a fix. This is always the first thing you should do.</li>
<li>Ask on the <a href="https://forums.freebsd.org/">FreeBSD Forums</a> for some help.</li>
<li>Check one of the FreeBSD mailing lists, and inform them, if there&rsquo;s a list relevant to dealing with your problem.</li>
<li>Hop into the FreeBSD IRC channels on Freenode. In my experience, people there are extremely helpful.</li>
<li>Submit a <a href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/">bug report</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Remember, if you do decide to ask the community for help with anything, be respectful, and be thorough. The time of the people involved in this community is valuable,
keep that in mind when dealing with them.</p>

<h3>Documentation</h3>

<p>There are two essential forms of documentation when you&rsquo;re using FreeBSD:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/">The FreeBSD Handbook</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.freebsd.org/cgi/man.cgi">The FreeBSD Manual Pages</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Best. Documentation. Ever.
Seriously, this project literally has the best documentation I&rsquo;ve ever seen. There&rsquo;s nothing left out, anywhere. Every minute detail is explained as clearly as possible in both
the handbook and the manual pages. I haven&rsquo;t, so far, needed to ask the community for help with general sysadmin stuff, because the details are all there in front of me.
I imagine if I ever submit a piece of documentation for inclusion in FreeBSD, it&rsquo;ll have to be of the highest standard, thorough, and it&rsquo;ll be scrutinised entirely, as it should be.
The point of documentation is to put you firmly in the driver&rsquo;s seat, and give you the power and control. This documentation gives you that power. All of it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m actually going to give OpenBSD a special mention here too. All of the BSDs have amazing documentation, but I personally think the BSD project closest to FreeBSD in terms of documentation
quality is OpenBSD. Their manual pages are absolutely superb.</p>

<h3>Some other notes</h3>

<ul>
<li>FreeBSD has always been a testbed for, and a leader in adoption of, new software and technology. Current examples include the LLVM/Clang C/C++ compiler, and the awesome ZFS filesystem.</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s not perfect on a laptop, there are some issues with suspend/resume on some laptop models. But it&rsquo;s improving, leaps and bounds, every day.</li>
<li>Its memory footprint is tiny, and that makes me really, really happy.</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s open source, under the BSD license. I don&rsquo;t want to get into a licensing flamewar, but the BSD license is awesome. It basically says, if you include this license in your docs, you can do whatever the hell you want with the code.</li>
<li>No systemd. Not now, not ever.</li>
</ul>


<p>NOTE: This is a work in progress. Any suggestions for inclusion or any errata you&rsquo;d like to point out can be sent to <a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;&#58;&#48;&#x78;&#x61;&#x31;&#x65;&#100;&#x40;&#x72;&#105;&#115;&#101;&#x75;&#x70;&#x2e;&#110;&#x65;&#x74;">&#x30;&#120;&#x61;&#x31;&#101;&#100;&#64;&#114;&#105;&#115;&#101;&#117;&#112;&#x2e;&#110;&#x65;&#116;</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
